<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: internet | No Rest For The Weekend]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.norestfortheweekend.com/blog/categories/internet/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.norestfortheweekend.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-04-29T22:37:48+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.norestfortheweekend.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Stickley]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's the difference between URL and URI?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.norestfortheweekend.com/blog/2009/09/13/whats-the-difference-between-url-and-uri/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-13T15:02:53+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.norestfortheweekend.com/blog/2009/09/13/whats-the-difference-between-url-and-uri</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Good question, and something I've often wondered. You hear people using both terms the whole time so let's lay this one to rest.</p>

<p>So I'm sitting in this café writing some code and probably looking like a bit of a geek. Fair enough, th<a href="http://atlantic-drugs.net/products/viagra.htm">viagra</a> happens. For various reasons I want to <a href="http://cvsmailorderpharmacy.org/buy-kamagra-usa.html">have</a> a variable in my webapp's registry that stores the URL of the current page. Or is it URI? I'm at a bit of a loss on what to call it.</p>

<h4>What is a URL?</h4>

<p>URL stands for <em>Uniform Resource Locator</em> which means it's a reference to a specific <em>location</em>. Importantly the location must be on the web, although this isn't indicated within it's name. More</p>

<h4>What is a URI?</h4>

<p>In relation to a URL<strong>a URI is like a superclass</strong>. It stands for <em>Uniform Resource Identifier</em> which means it's a reference to a specific <em>thing</em>. This thing could be just about anything addressable. For example a location on the web!</p>

<h4>What's the difference really? Why don't we just use URL?</h4>

<p>We should do if we are talking about web addresses! The distinction is that a URL provides information on how to get to the resource (Eg. http, https, ftp, mailto, etc). A URI can be relative (Eg. /path/to/file.jpg) or missing the protocol (Eg. //www.norestfortheweekend.com/2009/). These are both valid URIs but not URLs.</p>

<h4>Hidden Extras</h4>

<p>A URL <em>is a _ URI but a URI </em>is not necessarily_ a URL. We see this kind of relationship in programming with classes. Another 'subclass' of URI which not as many people have heard of is the URN.</p>

<p>URNs (Uniform Resource Name) start with <code>urn:</code> followed by a string identifying something. They are used for identification purposes rather than as a way of finding (locating) things as URLs are. Something that has some kind of universal identifier can be formatted as a URN. A good example of this is books. The majority of books at retail have an ISBN. The ISBN is their universal identifier; it doesn't point to where you can find the book, or contain any of the books subject matter. It just identifies it in a way that there is no confusion as to what you're talking about.</p>

<p>An ISBN can be expressed as a URN: <code>urn:isbn:1582408181</code>.</p>

<p>For more wordy explanations, check out the wikipedia articles on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform_Resource_Identifier">URIs</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform_Resource_Locator">URLs</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform_Resource_Name">URNs</a>!</p>

<p>  *[ISBN]: International Standard Book Number</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
